ILGWU Sol Chaikin Audio-Visual Materials 5780/083 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Sol Chaikin Audio-Visual Materials
1975-1986
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Chaikin, Sol
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/083 AV
8.11 cubic feet
8.1 linear ft.
Audio-visual materials.
The Sol Chaikin papers document Chaikin's tenure as president of the ILGWU from 1975 to 1986. Included in this collection are extensive correspondence, memoranda, and notes by and to Chaikin from ILGWU officers, staff, and members, politicians, and other labor leaders. Also included are transcripts of Chaikin's speeches, delivered to audiences of local union members, ILGWU and other international union conventions, United States Congress, international labor organizations, and others.
7461910
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 19, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Sol Chaikin was born in New York City January 9th, 1918. He graduated from Townsend Harris Hall High School in 1934. In 1940 he married Rosalind Bryon. Chaikin received a LL.B Degree from Brooklyn Law School. He then became an Organizer for the ILGWU, Local 178 in Fall River Massachusetts.
Chaikin held many union jobs through his lifetime.
1942-Business Agent, Local 281, Boston and Lowell, Massachusetts; 1943-U.S. Air Force; 1946- Manager, Local 22, ILGWU, Springfield, Massachusetts and Manager, Western Mass. District, Northeast Dept., ILGWU; 1955-Director, Lower Southwest Region, ILGWU; 1959-Assistant Director, Northeast Dept., ILGWU; 1965-Vice President, ILGWU; 1968-Chairman, American Trade Union Council for Histadrut; 1969-Associate Trustee, Long Island Jewish Hillside Medical Center; 1973-General Secretary-Treasurer, ILGWU; Vice-President, AFL-CIO Industrial Union Dept. Member, Board of Directors, New York Urban Coalition; 1975-President, ILGWU; Vice-President, AFL-CIO and Member, Executive Council Member, Governor's Task Force on Housing; 1976-Delegate to Democratic National Convention; Trade Union Council for Histadrut; 1977-Labor Representative, Belgrade Conference to Review Helsinki Accord on Human Rights; Head of AFL-CIO Delegation to International Labor Summit, London; Received Labor Human Rights Award, Jewish Labor Committee; 1978-Received Townsend Harris Award; Member, U.S. Delegation to Attend Funeral of Prime Minister Golda Meir; 1979-Present At Signing of Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty at the White House; 1980-Member, U.S. Delegation to ILO Session in Geneva; Vice-Chair, N.Y. Convention Center Operating Corp.; Member, Board of Trustees, Brandeis University; Honorary Degrees from Rutgers University and City University of New York; Seconded the Nomination of President Carter, Democratic National Convention; Published, A Labor Viewpoint: Another Opinion; 1982-Head, AFL-CIO Fact-Finding Mission to South Africa; Member, N.Y.S. Governor's Special Transit Advisory Panel; 1983-Hosted ZENSEN Delegation from Japan for Discussions of Apparel and Textile Industries; 1986-Retired as President of the ILGWU.
Sol Chaikin died April 1, 1991 at the age of 73.
Scope and Contents
The Sol Chaikin papers document Chaikin's tenure as president of the ILGWU from 1975 to 1986. Included in this collection are extensive correspondence, memoranda, and notes by and to Chaikin from ILGWU officers, staff, and members, politicians, and other labor leaders. Also included are transcripts of Chaikin's speeches, delivered to audiences of local union members, ILGWU and other international union conventions, United States Congress, international labor organizations, and others.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/083: ILGWU Sol Chaikin Papers 5780/083 P: ILGWU Sol Chaikin Photographs
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing trade -- United States; Chaikin, Sol C.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Southeast Region
7461910
- What's on your mind? April 28, 1984: Barry Gewen - ILGWU (Box 1)
- WCBS - Jane Tillman Ivy - 6/23/1984 (Box 2)
- 1985 Pines Hotel Seminar (Box 3)
- President Chaikin - 1985 (Box 4)
- Pine Seminar - 1985 (Box 5)
- Prof. Warner - Pine Seminar - 1985 (Box 6)
- Pres. Chaikin - Saturday - 1985 (Box 7)
- February 27, 1986 - Class V - Organized Labor an America's Future Workplace (Box 8)
- Phil Comstock on Immigration (Box 9)
- Chaikin Speech - @NYS-AFL-CIO Convention (Box 10)
- Item 807 (Box 11)
- Testimonial Dinner in honor of Sol Chaikin (Box 12)
- WLNA - Ginelle Tubner; ILG Imports - Mike Trinchi (Box 13)
- Sol Chaikin in Chile (Box 14)
- Benson - ILGWU (Box 15)
- Unlabeled (Box 16)
- Unlabeled (Box 17)
- A. is 1/2 hr.; B. 1/4 hr. (Box 18)
  Scope and Contents
  no other labeling
- ALNALL Community Comment - Rosa Mejias - ILGWU (Box 19)
- Access Guests: Starobin/Peretsman (Box 20)
- Sol Chaikin - Unity House - Upper South Conference - 8/27/1972 (Box 21)
- O'Brien & Chaikin - 10/19/1972 (Box 22)
- Allentown Dress Meeting - Nov. 14, 1972 (Box 23)
  Direct Presentation; Questions and Answers
- NE Institute - 2/2/1973, 1972 (Box 24)
- GEB Meet (last day session) Miami Beach, Tues, March 6, 1973 (Box 25)
- Sec. Treasurer Chaikin (Box 26)
- NE Unity House - 6/16 (Box 27)
- Local 190 - SDC Meeting - Aug. 21, 1973 (Box 28)
- Forward Association - 1/24/1974 (Box 29)
- District Council - 2/22/1974 (Box 30)
- Local 60-60A (Box 31)
- SCC Financial Report - 6/3/1974 (Box 32)
- SCC Nominations - 6/7/1974 (Box 33)
- Home Health Conference - 6/13/1974 (Box 34)
- Home Health Conference - 6/13/1974 (Box 35)
- Virginia AFL-CIO, Roanoke, Va. - 8/22/1974 (Box 36)
- Philadelphia Are Council Dinner meeting & Charter, Bellevue Stratford, Phila., 10/9/1974 (Box 37)
- ILG Pres Sol C. Chaikin, 1976 (Box 38)
  Addressing GA AFL-CIO Convention
- York - 2/22/1975 - Chaikin, Paul Smith (Box 39)
- Gov. R.H. Colon and Sec-Treas. - Sol C. Chaikin at the reception given by the GEB at the Caribe-Hilton, San Juan, P.R. - Mar. 5, 1975 (Box 40)
- Sol C. Chaikin - Guest Talk - March 19, 1975 (Box 41)
- Murray Finley Dinner, NYC - 4/5/1975 (Box 42)
- Histradrut - 5/13/1975 - New Haven, Ct. (Box 43)
- Philadelphia Area Council, Unity House - June 7, 1975 (Box 44)
- President (Chick) Chaikin's speech, 6/11/1975 (Box 45)
- SCC Loezz - 6/24/1975 (Box 46)
- SCC - Sept. 4, 1975 - NY Hilton - Staff Meeting (Box 47)
- LCLAA - Luncheon - Speakers - Inter. Pres. Of ILGWU Sol Chaikin (Box 48)
- Chaikin - Nov. 16, 1976 - Automation House (Box 49)
- NTUC Award Dinner - Jan. 12, 1977 (Box 50)
- SCC - The War College - 2/4/1977 (Box 51)
- SCC - The War College - 2/4/1977 (Box 52)
- NY State Labor History Society - CUNY Graduate Center, June 10, 1977 (Box 53)
- Steven Smith - WBZ Radio - Jun 16, 1977 (Box 54)
- Northeast Dept. - Unity House - June 25, 1977 (Box 55)
- Chick - ILGWU - July 22, 1977 (Box 56)
  Washington, DC; Upper South Dept. Organizing Institute - AFL-CIO Labor Studies Ctr.
- A Press Conf. - 5/23/1978 (Box 57)
- Cassette tape and transcript list, 1 (Box 58)
- Sol C. Chaikin - ACTWU Convention, Los Angeles CA, 2 (Box 58)
- Father Hesberg - Sixty Minutes - WCBS-TV - Mar. 14, Sun. 7 p.m., 3 (Box 58)
- Chaikin Speech before National convention of Social Democrats, USA ('81), 4 (Box 58)
- Paula Green Assoc. Institute of Collective Bargaining - Labor Looks at the Eighties #2 Featuring Sol Chaikin of the ILGWU, 5 (Box 58)
- Paula Green Inc. Adv. ILGWU "Democratic National Convention 8/20/1980, 6 (Box 58)
- Wanted: Experienced Operators, 7 (Box 58)
- Beit Aagen - English, 8 (Box 58)
- Pinnacle: ILGWU, 9 (Box 58)
- Sol Chaikin of the ILGWU - News - WOR TV Channel 9 - Weds. Jan. 25, 1978 at 12 noon, 10 (Box 58)
- Nomination of Jimmy Carter, August 13, 1980, 11 (Box 58)
- Chaikin - 1978-85 - Radio/TV Appearances: Good Morning America; WOR TV Interview; Multilateral Trade Negotiations; Today Show; 60 Min.; McNeil Lehrer Report, 12 (Box 58)
- ILGWU #235, 13 (Box 58)
- NTSC - Beit Hagefen, 14 (Box 58)
- Voice over of Mr. Chaikin, President, ILGWU - Liberal Party Dinner, 15 (Box 58)
- Sol Chaikin Recording for Murray Gross Dinner, 16 (Box 58)
- Sol Hoffman Luncheon, 17 (Box 58)
- Organized Labor's view of the American Labor Scene: Speaker: Mr. Sol C. Chaikin - 2/4/1977, 18 (Box 58)
- Thursday, June 28, 1984 - Barry Gewen, 19 (Box 58)
- Histadrut Humanitarian Award Presented to Sol C. Chaikin, Pres. ILGWU, Americana Hotel, January 24, 1978, 20 (Box 58)
- Chaikin Press Conference - Sept. 8, 1977, 21 (Box 58)
- Phila Area Council - Unity House 1975, 22 (Box 58)
- A Press Conference - 5/23/1978 (Box 59)
- Speech - Sol Chaikin at Vassar College - 2/5/1979 (Box 60)
- SCC - Opening of Archives - 1/24/1980 (Box 61)
- Contact: DeLora Hannaham - ILGWU - 1/1/1984 (Box 62)
- Brant Coleton - WHN - 4/12/1984 (Box 63)
- VISTA - W. Miriam Peretzman - 4/22/1984 (Box 64)
- Bob Ortiz - 4/29/1984 (Box 65)
- Audio digitized from the collection. (Box 66)